All right.
Today, we want to talk about investment banking, which is
different from commercial banking.
And today, we have a
guest, Jan Fugner, who took this
course, and he's going to talk about the
importance of investment banking.
アーモンド
10 years ago and has been working in investment banking
since.
I'll introduce him in a few minutes.
But I wanted to start
with just the elements of investment
banking, and then I wanted to
talk about changes in it that
came about after the financial crisis of 2007 through 2009.
So, OK, the topic is investment banking.
And that is a term, a
20th century term, that first became
big in the 1990s.
It was very important, I
would say, in the 1930s, but
preceded that by some years.
And it refers to a
business of helping other businesses create
securities.
If someone wants to issue stock, they go to an
investment banker to help them.
Or if you want to issue
bonds, you go to an investment banker.
It can be a corporation that goes to the for-profit.
It can be a non-profit corporation.
It can be a government.
I suppose even an individual
who is incorporated can go to
an investment bank.
That's the investment banking business.
Now, it differs, it shares something with the consulting
business.
It's not just a business.
It's a business.
Because investment bankers serve often as consultants.
A company will come to an investment banker with a
problem, and they want to raise money by issuing new
shares, for example, to solve that problem.
But if it's a good investment
bank, they will do more than
just issue shares for them.
They'll talk about their whole corporate strategy.
So, in that sense, an investment bank looks like a
consulting firm.
But that's not, because they don't do pure consulting.
They're not, that makes a distinction.
Maybe they're in many ways a favored consultant, because
they bring money.
You can talk to a consultant
who will bring you no money,
and another consultant who has his hands-on money somewhere,
and that helps a lot.
The advice and the money together helps a lot.
But it's not a good investment bank.
It's not a good investment bank.
So, investment bankers are different from traders,
because usually they deal with creating something, about
making a corporation or a government, making it work,
and enabling them to do
something that they want to do.
And then being realistic about
it, and coming up with the
money to do it.
And so, that's the way it works.
And so, that's how
investment banking differs from consulting.
And it differs from commercial banking, in that a pure
investment bank does not accept deposits.
You can't go to your investment
bank and say, I'd like to open
a savings account.
They don't do it.
Okay.
I'm talking about a pure investment bank.
Let me just give you some examples.
Let me just give you something about this business.
I'm going to come in a
moment to pointing out that most
investment banking businesses are not pure investment banks.
Let's talk about what a pure investment bank does.
It does underwriting of securities.
That means, suppose you're a company
and you want to issue a
share.
You need someone to go to bat for you.
Someone who knows the kind of
people who might buy your shares
and can vouch for you.
So, in some sense, it's a reputation thing.
The investment bank has contacts among people who make big
investments, and they manage the
issuance of your new shares,
and that's called an underwriting.
If it's the first time you've
issued shares, it's called an IPO,
or initial public offering.
So, you're a private company.
It's just you and a few friends
own the company, but now you want to
go public.
You would generally go to an
investment bank and talk to them
about how to do it.
And the investment bank would solve
that problem for you by doing an
underwriting.
So, traditionally, there's two kinds of underwriting.
There's also something called a seasoned offering.
And that means for a company
that has already gone public and it
already has shares traded, so that
the shares are seasoned, but you
want to issue more shares.
So, you can go to an
investment bank to do that as well.
Okay.
There's two kinds of deals.
There's a bought deal.
And then there's a best efforts.
With a bought deal, the investment bank buys your shares.
They go in and say, you know,
we know that we can market for your
shares.
We will buy them ourselves
and resell them on the market.
A best effort.
A best efforts offering is one
where the investment bank doesn't buy
it and doesn't promise anything.
They say, we'll make our
best efforts to place this offering.
Okay.
So, those are the basic things that they do.
The methods that they use are
regulated by the Securities and Exchange
Commission.
In order to make the SEC
in the United States and regulated similarly
in other countries.
So, that's the basic investment banking business.
So, if you're thinking of where
to place yourself, I think investment
banking suits very well people who
are, you know, in the business
world, people who are, it's not good for autistic people.
If you're autistic, be a trader.
Okay.
Then you just get on the phone
and you buy and sell all day.
And you can be rude and you
can have coffee stains on your shirt.
And you don't have to know anything about classical music.
Okay.
But investment bankers are a
different, I see Jan is laughing.
Tell me what you know about classical music.
I assume that was part of your training at Goldman.
Yeah.
He says no.
It's a different, it's a whole different industry.
So, yeah, if you go to the
symphony and look around, you'll see lots of
investment bankers there.
But you won't see any traders.
You're not on that, maybe.
So, you know, we talk about moral hazard.
I think that an important part of
what investment banks do is solve a moral
hazard problem.
And that problem is that companies
who issue shares don't have a reputation.
And so, you know, what do I care?
I'll issue shares right before we're going to go bankrupt.
Okay.
We know inside that we're going to go bankrupt.
So, hey, let's just see if we can
milk this company before the public knows it.
Okay.
And issue shares.
That's a moral hazard.
And the investment bank is in
business to prevent that moral hazard.
They do the due diligence.
They check you out.
And then after that, people are more trusting
of the – so, I think investment banking
is built around trust.
It's establishing trust.
And so, that's how it differs from a
lot of other – that's why it's important that
these people be cultivated and impressive.
They tend to be well-spoken, impressive people.
They're not.
I can ask Jan whether he agrees
on all this, but it's my impression.
You can tell when the
investment bankers walk in the room.
They dress differently.
They look differently.
I don't know what it is.
It's something about reputation is what it's built around.
So, okay.
The investment banking –
Let me just – since I'm talking about
the nature of investment banking, and since we
have a Goldman Sachs representative here, I put
on your reading list a book as an optional
reading by Charles Ellis.
It's called, The Financial Principle of Investment Banking.
It's a book by Charles Ellis.
It's called, The Partnership.
And it's a history of Goldman Sachs.
Goldman Sachs was an investment
bank until just very recently.
And we'll talk about that.
They're still in the investment banking business,
but now they're officially a commercial bank.
It's an old, venerable firm.
And Goldman Sachs emerged in the early 21st
century as, I think, the most highly respected
and esteemed investment bank in the world.
Amazingly successful and amazingly well respected.
Ellis wrote a book just a few years ago.
Ellis is on the European side.
He's a very successful businessman.
Ellis is on the Yale Corporation.
He's a distinguished businessman and author himself.
And he wrote a book about
Goldman Sachs, which is largely admiring.
Like how did this happen?
How did this phenomenon of Goldman Sachs come about?
And I suggested you read
one chapter, it was called Principles.
And it says,
I don't know if you've read it.
It's a very interesting chapter.
And it says something about Goldman Sachs.
And it refers to, in that chapter, the
chairman of Goldman Sachs, John Whitehead, in the 1970s,
wrote down a list of principles that guide Goldman Sachs.
And Ellis seems admiring of these principles.
Not everyone would agree.
It's a matter of taste, I guess, in living.
Whitehead is not.
I just looked it up.
He's 88 years old and is retired from Goldman.
Must have retired some years ago.
What kind of an organization?
Ellis says that the thing that
struck him about the organization is loyalty.
That people feel a strong loyalty toward their company.
That's not on Whitehead's list.
So Whitehead's list.
What is his first principle of Goldman Sachs?
Are clients' interests our interests?
Clients' interests always come first.
These sound a little bit like bromides.
I'm sorry.
But I read them thinking, it is
the most successful investment bank in the world.
So maybe there's something beyond.
I think there is something beyond platitudes here.
Second, our assets are people, capital, and reputation.
That's coincident with what I said.
Uncompromising determination to achieve everything.
To achieve excellence.
Well, everybody says that.
So maybe we discount that.
We stress creativity and imagination.
Well, those are sort of bromides, maybe.
Then Whitehead issued some guidelines.
This is also in that
chapter later for Goldman Sachs employees.
And these seem to be a little bit more candid.
The boss usually decides, not the assistant treasurer.
Do you know the boss?
Okay.
That's sort of something that I've
learned from my own interaction with people.
The boss really does decide.
And Goldman Sachs goes for the top.
And maybe this is obnoxious.
I don't know.
They don't want to talk with underlings.
You never learn anything when you're talking.
Okay.
It means be a good listener.
The respect of one person is
worth more than the acquaintance with 100.
There's nothing worse than an underling.
There's nothing worse than an unhappy client.
But one thing that, I don't know if it's
on Whitehead's list, but I think it really says
something about investment banking, and that
Ellis says, is that they shun publicity.
They don't want to be in the newspaper.
They want to be known by the president.
They want to be known by a few prominent people.
They're kind of social climbers in a way.
But it's all built around some basic principles of service.
And they want to be talking to the top.
They want to be the top guy.
And they don't want to be in the newspaper.
I was going to quote Ellis on this.
And now I'm quoting Charlie Ellis.
I call him Charlie.
I know him.
He's a friend of mine.
Making money, always and no exceptions,
was a principle of Goldman Sachs.
Nothing was ever done for prestige.
In fact, it was never done for prestige.
It was never done for prestige.
In fact, the most prestigious
clients were often charged the most.
Absolute loyalty to the firm
and to the partnership was expected.
Personal anonymity was almost a core value.
The real culture of Goldman Sachs was a unique
blend of drive for making money and the characteristics
of family in ways that the Chinese,
Arabs, and old Europeans would well understand.
So, I'm giving you a flavor
of what an investment bank is.
You might be repelled by it.
You know, is making money so important?
And if you are repelled by it, you
probably don't want to work for Goldman Sachs.
On the other hand, they're kind
of respecting some economic principles, right?
Working for a firm like this,
you can make huge amounts of money.
And then, at the end, you
can give it all away to charity.
And that's the new capitalism, right?
So, what's wrong with that?
What are you going to do with all this?
If you make $100 million, what
are you going to do with it?
You're going to give it away, right?
And maybe, I mentioned at the beginning,
I mentioned Andrew Carnegie's book, The Gospel
of Wealth.
Maybe that's what this is all about.
On the other hand, some of them don't
give it away and some of them live lavishly.
So, I don't know.
Different people have different
impressions of this business.
But I want to make sure I have time for
our guests and I'm sort of running out of time.
I wanted to talk about
what has happened in the crisis.
There's so much to say about this topic.
But maybe I should talk first about the first crisis.
In 1933, the U.S. Congress passed the Glass-Steagall Act.
Which forced investment banks and which
prevented investment banks from doing commercial banking
or commercial banks from doing investment banking.
It split them in two.
And it said, you have to decide, are you
a commercial bank or are you an investment bank?
The Glass-Steagall Act was the
act that created the U.S. Congress.
It created the FDIC,
the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation.
The first national, successful national
deposit insurance act in the world.
And part of it, it makes sense.
If you're going to insure the commercial
banks, you better watch what they're doing.
And prevent them from doing dangerous business.
So, the dangerous business was investment banking.
And they forced companies to decide.
And Morgan Stanley, which was doing both
investment banking and commercial banking in 1933,
had to decide.
What is it?
Investment banking or commercial banking?
So, they picked commercial banking.
And that means they fired all of their investment bankers.
So, these guys regrouped and they
formed another investment bank called Morgan Stanley.
Stanley was a Yale graduate.
And Morgan was, I think, not
J.P. Morgan, it was his grandson.
This was, you know, Morgan died around 1911.
And so, those were two
separate, one, J.P. Morgan, commercial bank.
Morgan Stanley, investment bank.
But since then, we've repealed the Glass-Steagall Act.
And that occurred with the Graham-Leach Act of,
what was that, 1999?
Well, Graham-Leach repealed Glass-Steagall.
And now, these businesses generally do
the same business, both commercial and, yeah,
Graham-Leach was 1999.
Okay.
Since then, you might, as you
recall, we've had a financial crisis.
And in that financial crisis,
Glass-Steagall got brought up again.
Because it seemed that the crisis was related
to a number of shenanigans that firms were undertaking.
And the government had to bail out commercial banks.
And you may have, we've talked about this.
And it's very controversial.
So, the question is, did these banks
get in trouble because we repealed Glass-Steagall?
A lot of people came on saying that.
These banks were doing all kinds
of screwy things that were dangerous.
And we're insuring them, so it can't be.
So, a lot of people
said, we have to go back.
There was some inherent wisdom
in Glass-Steagall that we've lost.
And this was debated.
Now, incidentally, I didn't mention this.
Glass-Steagall was somehow confined to the United States.
Outside of the United States, there was, I don't know
if there was any country, but as far as I know,
the U.S. was the only one that did it.
So, outside of the United States,
they had what was called universal banking.
And these banks outside of the U.S.
were doing both investment banking and commercial banking.
They sailed right through the
whole century without being divided up.
And so, the reason why we got Gramm-Leach
was that we started to, people started to say,
you know, we're at a competitive disadvantage.
We Americans are at a competitive disadvantage
to Europe because we can't do both.
And they have more freedom than we.
And so, eventually, in 1999, we
said they could, they could do it.
We said they could do both.
So, the U.S. also became a universal banking country.
But then problems arose.
And the problems were Paul Volcker, who, Paul
Volcker, who was chairman of the Federal Reserve Board
in the late 70s, early 80s.
Proposed something called the Volcker Rule.
And the Volcker Rule was not a full return to,
was not a full return to investment of the Glass-Steagall.
But it would.
And this is now in Dodd-Frank Act.
It's Section 619.
It doesn't say Volcker Rule
there, but that's what it is.
And it prohibits proprietary trading at commercial banks.
And it also says that banks can't, commercial banks can't,
own hedge funds or private equity.
So, that's the, that was the
Volcker Rule that was put in.
There was also another rule added,
which is analogous to the Dodd-Frank Act.
Also, and this is in the Dodd-Frank Act of 2010.
There was a senator.
He was a senator.
Her name was Blanche Lincoln, a Democrat from Arkansas,
who proposed the Lincoln Rule, unrelated to
Abraham Lincoln, as far as I know.
And the Lincoln Rule was, or
Lincoln Amendment, and that is Section 710.
Section 716 of Dodd-Frank.
It says that it doesn't prohibit
banks dealing in credit in swaps.
But it says swap dealers borrowed access
to the Fed, to Fed window, discount window.
And so, effectively, it prevents
banks from dealing in swaps anymore.
As a result of this, Goldman Sachs has got
to shut down, or it appears that Goldman Sachs,
the Volcker Rule says banks
have until October 2011 to comply.
So, it means that Goldman Sachs has to shut down.
Well, it's not a good thing.
Goldman Sachs had to become a commercial bank, too.
So, it's no longer a pure,
it's an official commercial bank now.
And because of the Volcker Rule, it appears
that it has to shut down its proprietary trading,
which was a huge part of its profits.
And Goldman Sachs will never be the same again, apparently.
But it's not clear what will happen.
It depends all on how Dodd-Frank is enforced.
I think that people in investment banking industry are
going to try to claim that some of the activity
that was done by their proprietary traders, that is,
people who were trading the markets on the –
I understand true investment banking shouldn't involve
the investment banker buying and selling securities,
trying to make a profit.
That's not underwriting of securities.
That's proprietary trading.
Volcker Rule says that you pretty much can't do
it anymore, unless you were a pure investment bank.
But if you're a commercial
bank, you can't do it anymore.
And they're kind of forced to become a commercial bank.
But they're going to try to steer around these rules.
And I think that maybe they can.
They'll redefine something that
looks something like proprietary trading.
And then, you know, it's a good thing.
And then continue to do what they're doing.
We'll have to see.
These things are long and arduous.
You know, one thing that strikes me
about finance is that it's so rules-based.
There are so many laws.
There are so many lawyers that you can never – nobody
can grasp the magnitude of the regulations that these people live under.
And, you know, you see these landmark bills, but none of us understand them, because the real content of
them is involved in hundreds of pages of legal documents that never cease to amaze me with their complexity.
So, let me say something about
shadow banking, which is relevant here.
The term shadow banking.
I think of that as coming from a term that I first
heard from people at PIMCO just within the last five years or so.
But it refers to – maybe
it goes back further than that.
It refers to a new kind of
semi-banking system that – what are shadow banks?
These are companies that are actually –
these are companies that are acting like commercial banks, but
they're technically not, so they're not regulated as commercial banks.
And in many cases, the investment banks were shadow banks.
And I'll give you an example of
Lehman Brothers, which was a pure investment bank.
It's now bankrupt.
It's gone.
It was a pure investment bank, so
it wasn't regulated as a commercial bank.
And it –
this was before the Volcker Rule, before Dodd-Frank.
And they went bankrupt in 2008.
And it was the worst moment in the financial crisis.
Why did they go bankrupt?
Well, there's a reading I have on your reading list
by Professor Gary Gorton here at Yale, who argues that,
Lehman, like many other investment banks, was financing a lot
of proprietary investments by issuing repos, or by dealing in repos.
What is a repo?
That's short for repurchase agreement.
And the banking crisis that we saw in
2008 was substantially a run on the repo.
So, here's what happened, according to
Gorton and others who agree with him.
Investment banks like Lehman Brothers
were not regulated like commercial banks.
And as long as they didn't accept deposits,
they didn't have to be regulated as commercial banks.
So, they could do what they wanted.
They were considered underwriters, so
fine, do whatever you want.
Well, not quite, but they weren't
heavily regulated the way commercial banks were.
And what Lehman Brothers started to do is to make heavy investments
in subprime securities and other securities by effectively borrowing through the repo market.
And what is the repo market?
It's a market in which a company effectively borrows money by
effectively selling some securities it owns with an agreement in place.
With an agreement to repurchase
the security at a later date.
They're short-term loans, in fact, collateralized
by some security that they own.
What it was, is almost the same as a deposit.
They were short-term loans that
someone could withdraw at any time.
The someone wouldn't be some mother
and father with their small savings account.
It would be some bigger, probably institutional investor.
But these were acting like banks, like commercial banks, because there could be a
run on these banks the same way there's a run on a commercial bank.
If anyone starts fearing that Lehman Brothers is going to fail, they all
want to take their money out, which means they don't renew their repos.
And so, Lehman Brothers failed when the housing
market declined, the value of its subprime securities declined.
People who were lending its money through repos,
they didn't want to take their money out.
They didn't want to take their money out.
So, Lehman Brothers, who were lending their money through repos,
got wind of this, and they stopped wanting to do it.
So, it was like a run on Lehman Brothers.
And Lehman Brothers could not be
saved if it weren't for a bailout.
And the government had already bailed out Bear Stearns, and
it had helped Merrill Lynch, which was failing as well.
And they decided not to bail everybody out.
And Lehman Brothers failed.
So, now, the reaction to that is
that we can't let shadow banking go unregulated.
And Dodd-Frank is part of that reaction.
So, now, investment banking is
substantially altered by these laws.
And it's still, of course, it's a very important business.
The United States has traditionally been
the most important country in investment banking.
But it continues that Europe and Asia are
also important, very important participants in investment banking.
The financial crisis has put something of
a damper on the business for a while.
But I think it seems to be coming back.
The latest news is that investment banking business
is starting to look more stable and prosperous.
So, I think what I want to do now
is invite, let me just do a brief introduction.
So, Jan Fugner took this
class, I think it was 2002.
And then he served as my research assistant for
a book I was writing called New Financial Order.
So, I got to know him better.
Then, well, I guess you, the important thing for this lecture is
that you worked for Goldman Sachs and got to know people there.
And now is working for Facebook.
Yes.
You've heard of this company, right?
I thought it would be interesting to have him back to
give his impressions of what life was like after Econ 252.
Of what Goldman Sachs was like.
At least the old Goldman Sachs.
And I think, you know, it's interesting to hear about
Facebook too because it's a different kind of culture and,
I'm interested in culture.
It's more of a tech business.
I'm interested to hear if they have anything like the
Goldman Sachs principles where they enunciate them the same way.
So, I'll bring Jan up and I'll let him continue.
Great.
Well, thank you, Professor Schiller.
And Professor Schiller has promised that
I'll be well spoken and well-dressed.
And a bunch of other things, good, bad or otherwise.
Not sure if I'll live up to any of those
expectations but hopefully can share a little bit about this business.
How many of you are
considering going into investment banking?
Maybe about 30% or so.
Okay.
And how many of you are on Facebook?
And how many of you are
considering going into the investment banking industry?
Okay.
And how many of you are considering working at Facebook?
So, maybe we'll add a few more
to that by the end of this.
Goal for the next half hour is really to help you think
about whether banking might be the right next step for you after college.
And for those of you who say yes, to share a
few tips on how to think about getting into the business.
So, I'll give a little bit of my background kind of as context for
my reflections on the industry so you can take them with a grain of salt.
Share some anecdotes from banking during the debt boom and then also give a
few tips for steps that you can take today if you're interested in it.
So, a little on my background.
Junior summer, I went and worked at
a large investment bank as Professor Schiller mentioned.
And I really enjoyed the work, knew
that I wanted to go back to it.
But I had never lived abroad because as you all know, your junior year here
at Yale, there's a lot going on with extracurriculars and so many people don't go abroad.
I went to see Charles Hill.
Now, how did he do?
How many folks are familiar with Charles Hill?
Fabulous negotiator.
And I said, Professor Hill, how can I negotiate to go back to
this job a year later so I can do a Fulbright in the meantime?
So, he taught me all this
jujitsu and it ended up working out.
And I did a year in Norway
and then came back full time to banking.
Now, as you probably know, a lot of analysts
go into banking, they do it for two years.
Maybe do private equity, hedge
fund, maybe do an MBA afterwards.
And something like 15% might stay on.
Get promoted and become career track bankers.
When I was working on Wall Street, this was the peak
of the most recent private equity boom and the associated debt boom.
And so, recruiting to private equity had reached such a fever pitch that literally 16 months before the start
date for these jobs, analysts were getting calls from recruiters, doing interviews and actually making commitments to join these companies.
And I knew I was interested in tech.
And so, I became very close to science.
And so, I became very close to signing with a technology
private equity fund that I admire still very much to this day.
But I actually decided that I
wanted to work in tech itself.
And so, the last three and a half years, as you
mentioned, I've been working at Facebook, working on our social advertising strategy.
So, a little bit about inside the banking role.
It may sound a little bit funny to talk
about the investment banking division of an investment bank.
But that's what we'll do for the next 15 minutes.
And by that, I really mean
just the part of the business.
And so, I'm going to talk about the business that Professor Schiller
mentioned, giving advice to CEOs and CFOs about financing and mergers and acquisitions.
So, if you see this
logo, and that makes you smile.
I see a few smiles, maybe a couple of grimaces.
If it makes you smile, that's a
good sign that banking may be for you.
You think about two, three, four...
They don't understand that.
That's an Excel logo, right?
That's an Excel logo.
What are you driving?
And these are Excel models.
And they go on and on.
You mean you're going to be a nerd.
Is that what you're saying?
Yeah.
If by that you mean you want to feel
comfortable with the technical aspect of the role, yeah, absolutely.
So, especially at the junior level where you
mentioned some of the relationship aspects of banking.
But at the junior level, really your
core responsibility is building out these models.
So, if you think about working on that until
four in the morning, maybe two nights in a row.
Maybe 20 nights in a row.
And that's exciting to you.
That's a good sign.
So, how many of you have gone online to
open Yale to see Steven Schwarzman's talk from this
class three years ago?
One, two.
Two enterprising users of the Internet.
Would strongly encourage everyone to do that.
One of the things that he talks about is
that in banking, there's not a ton of time to
fix the problem.
It's a lot of time.
It's a lot of time, but it's
a lot of time to fix the problem.
It's a lot of time.
And at the end of the day, it's a
lot of time that you spend on the internet.
And one of the things that he talks about
is that in banking, there's not a ton of time
to fix the problem.
You can't fix the problem when you go there.
One, two, two enterprising users of the
internet would strongly encourage everyone to do that.
One of the things that he talks about is
that in banking there's not a ton of flexibility
for getting the numbers wrong.
As the analyst, you really need to nail
the details and primarily what we're talking about
there is building operating transaction and
valuation models that describe your clients
and other companies in their industry.
And then the information from those models along
with research you find by hook and by
crook on the internet from your colleagues,
wherever you can, kind of comes together into
presentations, polished pitch books to
help win a piece of business.
So that could be an IPO,
a merger advisory as you mentioned.
And once you've won that piece of business,
then you as the analyst really are the organizing
principle for getting this deal across
the finish line, dealing with the accountants,
working with the lawyers.
So you're not just going to be working
with the lawyers, you're going to be working with
the bankers, the other bankers, even competitors
who might also be working on the deal.
And then of course your client and
whichever counterparty your client is selling to or
buying from.
So it's a fair amount of responsibility.
Typical investment banking deal team, the core
team is pretty lean, maybe one each of
an analyst, associate, VP and MD.
And if you decide to and are given
the opportunity to continue working in investment banking
on a career basis.
You're going to have to have a lot of
control over your week to week and month to month
schedule as you become more senior.
But even at a senior level, investment banking
is really considered an always on call client
service profession.
Now one of the advantages of this very
lean deal team is that there's plenty of responsibility
to go around.
If you raise your hand and say, yeah, I can
take on some of this work that might by default
fall to my associate and you do it
without making mistakes, you're going to be able to
get more and more responsibility, learn
more and more on the job.
So one of my favorite projects that I worked on is the
one that I worked on, which is the one that I worked on.
It was a proposed venture capital transaction where we
were looking at investing in eight different operating companies.
And because the team was that lean, I was actually able to
basically take on leading the due diligence on these eight different companies.
Before you go ahead, why do
the managing directors have zero gray hairs?
I'm just assuming it's all gone by then.
Okay.
Yeah.
It's a median.
The mean might be a little bit higher.
It's high variance.
Yeah.
We're looking at very high variance.
So I would...
Was that the nerdy comment you were looking for?
So I might encourage you to think about
these roles as an investment in your career, where
what you put in, of course, is long hours,
maybe a hundred hours a week for a couple
of years, and what you get out is a
number of things including a skill set that's really
valued and respected not just in finance
but around the business world, exposures to CFOs
the CFOs and how they think about problems, if
you decide to continue on as a career banker,
participation in the success that you help
create for your company, and then, of course,
a network of very smart, eager peers like the
folks in this room who then fan out across
the finance industry.
So as I mentioned, I was banking during the
debt boom, and there was such a peak in transactions
that people started calling it merger Mondays,
this expectation that before the bell at the
beginning of the week, there'd be a $20
billion or $30 billion, $40 billion transaction that'd
be announced.
And there was so much enthusiasm for
this sort of transaction that even financial institutions,
which conventional wisdom told us couldn't
be LBOed because their balance sheets were
already so levered, actually became
considered targets for leveraged buyouts.
And arguably, the peak of this was when
Blackstone themselves, one of the fathers of the buyout
industry, filed an S-1 and, in
fact, became a publicly traded company.
Which is a great thing.
Which they are to this day.
Your final task as a banking analyst is
to create a deal toy when you successfully created
a transaction.
Now, this particular one used to have water
in it and glittering fish, and at the time,
I thought it was very pretty.
But I would just invite you, maybe, when
you create your deal toys, don't picture your
client swimming with the fishes.
Not the best idea.
And then this is a safe for
a bank, which, of course, is logical.
Safes are in a bank.
But this is actually an especially fun toy
because you pull this handle here and then
actually this one opens up.
Well, that was my idea of
fun when I was a banker.
So you, again, take it with a grain of salt.
This is a snow globe.
You shake it upside down, which
is a lot of fun as well.
But again, just in terms of the
metaphor, and I have only myself to blame.
Maybe I was sleep deprived.
I guess maybe don't show your
client's capital structure literally underwater when you,
when you design your deal toys.
Are you saying our investment bankers have a childish side?
You say deal toys.
I was presenting them as going to the symphony.
What are you presenting them as?
I can't claim I ever made it
to the symphony when I was an analyst.
But a number of my colleagues were
on the boards involved philanthropically with those
organizations.
But yeah, I think that we
have this creative energy and creative spirit.
And I think there's a lot of creativity in finance.
As Stephen Schwartz said, I think
there's a lot of creativity in finance.
And I think that's what Stephen
Schwartz's been mentioned in his talk.
At the senior levels when
you're dreaming how to combine companies,
how to finance companies, how to
deal with new regulation, as you mentioned.
But at the analyst level, maybe not quite as much.
So maybe there is that creative spark
that's just trying to find its way out,
you know, one mischievous way or another.
But anyway, this was the landscape when
I left banking, that was September 2007.
And then six months after that, as Professor
Shiller mentioned, Bear Stearns sold in a fire sale
to JP Morgan.
And then six months after that, September 2008,
we saw Merrill Lynch narrowly avert liquidation,
become the asset management brand of Bank of America,
which it still is today.
That same week, Lehman Brothers collapsed
under the weight of those mortgages, suffered a bank run,
and was not bailed out.
It was liquidated, and some of their investment banking,
capital markets assets sold to Barclays in bankruptcy.
A week after that, what a lot of people thought
would never happen did happen.
And Goldman Sachs and Morgan Stanley
went to the Federal Reserve,
asked to become commercial banks,
which technically they still are today,
as Professor Shiller mentioned.
Now that having been said,
if you take Charles Gasparino's account of this era,
this was the end of an era for Wall Street.
That having been said, investment banking continued
at firms all around the world,
some of these diversified conglomerates.
And also at a burgeoning slate of so-called
independent advisory shops.
These are folks like Evercore, Lazard, Greenhill.
And if you're interested in learning about finance,
investment banking is not the
only way to get into it.
There are also, for example, the so-called
alternative asset managers, private equity and hedge funds,
folks like KKR, Carlyle, Bridgewater,
who I believe still recruits here on campus.
And then out where I live in California,
you have the heart of
the venture capital industry, especially,
the venture capital industry, which
is the venture capital industry.
It's actually around the information technology industry.
So folks like Kleiner, Sequoia, Benchmark.
Now they may not be recruiting on campus, and
they may not even be open to hiring undergraduates, but
some of their competitors are.
So if that's interesting to you,
maybe we'll just touch on a
few steps that you can take today.
Obviously you're already doing plenty of
this without anyone having to remind you
things like taking the right classes, doing well in them,
researching the firms you want to apply to.
There's three that I'll
touch on.
Taking advantage of the incredible resource you have and
the professors here today, which you
really don't want to take for granted.
Learning a little bit about yourself, and
I know that sounds touchy feely, but
I'll give a couple specifics around that.
And then of course there's no substitute for
trying this hands on to see whether it suits you.
So this is pretty much
exactly as I remember John Giannacopoulos,
genius mad scientist.
You can find him on Open Yale now.
And if you have not yet taken
his class and it's offered next year,
I would strongly recommend that you do so.
David Swenson, I understand you've had
the distinct pleasure of hearing from already
the most successful endowment manager ever,
the reason that we get to
have nice things here at Yale.
And I just keep coming back
time and again to pioneering portfolio management,
the bedrock of core investing principles
that he articulates in that book.
Even if you never become an institutional investor
and are only thinking as a real investor,
you're going to be able
to do a lot of things.
And I think that's the key to this.
So, again, I think that's the key to this.
A little bit of a back and forth,
but I do think as a real investor,
still incredibly useful stuff.
And he does teach a senior seminar.
And then in addition to
this class, as you probably know,
Professor Schiller has a graduate seminar,
which I think you have promised to
let students apply to, to get into.
Yeah, I had about eight last semester.
Okay. And how'd they do?
That's an embarrassing thing.
They did pretty well.
I think, against our graduate students.
Okay.
I won't rank them.
Embarrassing to our students.
I mean, if you want to be the first
person, if you want to be the first person,
our graduate students.
But flattering to all of you.
As Professor Schiller mentioned, I got to work a
little bit on new financial order as an undergraduate.
And I just still consider it such a rewarding experience.
Because the tenets that you
talk about in this book around
how finance can be a technology for societal
innovation, everything from the micro level of personal
income insurance to encourage people to take more risks
early on in their careers,
to the macro level of GDP
insurance, are some really visionary ideas.
I, of course, remain dismayed
that some of them have not
been put into practice yet.
But that really is an
opportunity for all of you who
are interested in finance for idealists to think about that
as a potential career option.
Other useful courses, of course, anything with math,
probability, stats, econometrics, cell modeling,
especially using the three financial statements,
computer science, computer programming, is going to
serve you well, not just in investment banking, which we're
talking about this morning, but also in those other aspects
of financial services, like trading.
Now, switching gears a little
bit, how many of you have
either done Myers-Briggs or Strength Finder?
A few, maybe 20, maybe 30% or so.
So these are tools that I
think have become a little bit more
popular in recent years, which are basically psychological
inventories, where you spend an hour.
You're answering multiple choice questions.
And then they literally spit out
a profile of how you like
to work.
Obviously, there's no right or wrong answers.
They're really just preferences.
It's a pretty modest investment
of your time, maybe an hour
each, to gain insight, not just
into what you're good at, but
also into helping you articulate to potential
employers really what you can bring to the table.
And then, of course, where
the rubber meets the road is
actually applying for that internship or that job and
getting your foot in the door.
Career services on campus are a fabulous resource.
But because of that, they're a very scarce resource, because
almost everyone's using them.
So if you want to find
jobs that don't get 200 other Yale
resumes coming in their front
door, you want to look a
little further afield.
So you've got things like lists of investment management
firms, from institutional investor, American Banker,
hedge fund research.
There are plenty of these lists.
And I'd say don't be
shy about cold calling, cold emailing.
Just kind of be persistent.
We touched on professors here.
I am incredibly grateful to Professor Schiller, Ray Fair,
David Swenson, folks who have helped
me in my career, even at
this extremely early stage in my career.
And it was really just because I asked.
And I'd encourage you to
do the same thing, because once
you've left campus, it gets a
lot harder to get that help.
And then the alumni directory.
How many folks have been
using the alumni directory to reach
out for jobs?
Maybe 15%.
I'd encourage you to do so.
And all I would add to that
is think about what you share in
common with the people you're reaching out to.
Think about whether you can reciprocate the help that
you're asking for, even if
that might not be obvious now,
because they're establishing their career and you're just
starting out.
I had a student in this
class reach out to me three weeks
ago, interested in advice.
And I was happy to share that.
And actually, he ended up being really helpful, helping me
understand where you all are in your decision making process
in your career right now.
So there are always ways that
you can reach out to me.
You can help.
And you'll find a much more
welcome hand if you're able to
do that.
And then lastly, recruiters.
These large so-called 2 in 20 funds, the alternative asset
managers, typically use third party recruiters to find the
talent that they want to interview.
And they are typically targeting current banking
analysts and associates.
But there's nothing to say that
if you have a strong finance
and technical background as
an undergraduate that you couldn't
actually get on there.
If they had a really strong
position, if they had a strong
position in their field, you
wouldn't be on their radar and
try to use them for a placement.
The only caveat I would add to
that is that you want to be
really clear and confident when you
speak to them about what it
is that you're looking for.
Because if you go in
there waffling, asking them to sort
of be your mentor and your career coach, they're really
not going to get that sense of confidence for you.
And they're not going to want to
put you in front of one of
their clients, who are the asset management.
We're gonna open it up for questions
in a minute, but go ahead and...
This should probably come at the end.
I was wondering, who's Keith Ferrazzi?
How many folks are familiar
with Keith Ferrazzi in the room?
Some people, their arms are getting tired.
Maybe 20%.
So Keith was the youngest ever Fortune 500
CMO, and he's a fellow Yaley, New York Times
bestselling author, written a lot about
the role that relationships play in business.
And you hear this word networking, right?
Which I think all of us now
kinda get a sort of unctuous feel around.
It seems very sort of superficial and self-serving.
And what he's really helped elucidate is how
the basic tenets of psychology, and in this
respect he reminds me of Professor Schiller,
applying the basic tenets of psychology to
how you actually build real meaningful
business relationships, and breaking down this artificial
barrier between relationships and business.
Because business is relationships.
Professor Schiller mentioned, one of the things
that investment bankers try to do is
establish senior level relationships because
it's ultimately individuals, not entire companies
who are making decisions.
So just to share a couple
anecdotes about my transition from banking.
After banking, as I said, I
knew I wanted to work in tech.
And I very fortuitously got a phone call
from a lifelong friend of mine around that time
who was an engineer who had started working at Facebook.
And what he convinced me was that I
could help him and his colleagues change how people
communicate.
And I was pretty sort of anxious about
this, pretty intimidated by the prospect of being
a business guy joining an engineering company.
And what he told me, and I ultimately think
this proved true, is that you don't have to
be an engineer in Silicon Valley to have an
impact, you just have to be able to think
rigorously like an engineer does.
I think the training that you're doing here at
Yale, I think you're doing it in a very
competitive way.
And I think that's what I'm trying to do.
And then the potential training of investment
banking both have the potential to serve you
well in that respect.
So what we're trying to do at Facebook is
give people the power to share and make the
world more open and connected.
Pretty simple principle, and our strategy for
doing this is mapping out what we call
a social graph.
Now, we didn't create this,
this exists out in the world.
All we're trying to do is draw
a mathematical representation of it, and that's basically
who likes whom and who likes what.
And then we push information as a Facebook.
And then we push information as efficiently
as possible along the edges of that graph.
So this is kind of where I spend most
of my day, not just over here in Farmville, but
also over here in Adsland.
And what my role is
called is local inbound product marketing.
So to kind of parse that out, what we
mean is basically I go and talk to local businesses,
restaurants, plumbers, understand what
their pain points are.
What other advertising products they use, what
they're trying to accomplish as a local
business owner, and then basically synthesize
that with data analysis and ultimately present
it to the engineers as a
case for what we should build next.
So these are questions like what are the
ads that you see on Facebook look like?
How should they interact with the rest of the product?
How can we target them to
make them more relevant to you?
A whole bunch more.
The real guiding precept here is that
it's basically what Henry Ford said, right?
He said, you know, you're
going to be a good salesman.
You're going to be an amazing salesman.
You're going to be a brilliant salesman.
You're going to be a great entrepreneur.
And he didn't want to build the faster
horse, even if that's what his clients might have
asked for, he wanted to build
something that was dramatically more useful.
And for him, that was the car.
And for us, it's something that we call social advertising.
I'm happy to chat a little bit more
about that during questions if folks are interested.
So finally, just to kind of compare these
two roles and how one might have prepared
me for the other, I think the three
things for banking that have served me best working
on Internet products are one, this just
cross-functional process management, which is a ubiquitous thing.
And I think that's going to be one of
the things that I'm going to focus on in the
part of the business world. Two,
building polished presentations, this one notwithstanding.
And three, being resourceful about tracking down
data points to help make the right decisions.
On the other hand, there's some parts of
the job that were totally new, thinking from the
mindset of the CMO, the chief marketing officer,
rather than the CFO, the chief financial officer.
Just the pace of the environment. Banking
is fast-paced, but the rate at which products
evolve in the internet is dramatically faster.
And the fundamental job itself, which is basically
creating new products, building the business case
for them, validating that case with data,
trying to actually mock them up, and I assure
you I'm not good in Photoshop, and then actually
use those mocks in that case to inspire
engineers and product managers to want to build them.
So it's an environment that is much more
ambiguous. The yardsticks for whether or not you're going
in the right direction.
And the things that I'm going to talk
about today, especially in the short term, are
not nearly as clear. But if that's
actually something that's appealing to you, then I'd
strongly encourage you to check out jobs
around Silicon Valley and especially at Facebook.
So you can actually go to facebook.com slash
careers, quick plug, to check out both the
internships and the full-time jobs that we have available.
So Professor Schiller, did you want to
use the rest of the time for questions?
Well, yeah. I'm opening it up
to all of you for questions.
Okay.
So, okay, you have a question back there.
Before you did your junior summer investment
banking, how did you even know you wanted
to enter?
I caught some of that and then the screen
caught some of it, so just bear with us for
one second and then I'll be right with you.
You said before I did my
junior summer, what did I do?
Before you did your junior summer or
like how did you figure out that investment
banking would be a field and what you want?
Well, you know, I knew that some of the
stuff on the right-hand column of the ROI chart
was stuff I was interested in. I was
interested in the technical side of the work, working
on math basically, but also interested in
the relationship side of it, the strategic
side, thinking about basically how you help
these companies make, bet the company's worth.
I'm not an expert on the technical side of it. But I was interested in the relationship side
of it, the strategic side, thinking about basically how you help these companies make bet the company's worth.
Okay.
So you mentioned evaluation is a one-trick
decision.
Yeah.
Okay.
great in the world was really appealing to me.
And I hadn't done Strength Finder yet at
the time, but I did it subsequently and found,
not surprisingly, that that's kind of
where my psychological reward structure was kind
of geared towards.
Tom?
Hello.
Hey.
So Peter Thiel, who was the first investor
in Facebook and is currently on their board,
is now offering 20 people under the age of
20 each $100,000 to drop out of school for
two years and start their own companies.
And since you actually work for Facebook,
I was wondering what you thought of that.
Yes, I think that's fascinating.
And obviously I don't work with Peter Thiel.
Look, I think whatever we can
do to promote innovation is great, right?
Now if you're sitting here in this room and
saying, well, do I want to take this risk
of sacrificing this signaling device of the...
This college degree and also potentially
sacrificing some structured classroom experience in order
to kind of rapidly accelerate how quickly
I get into entrepreneurship, I don't know.
That's a personal decision that is for you
to make and I don't really have any opinion
on it.
Ultimately, for me, it'll come down to
do these companies actually end up doing really
cool things and building really cool stuff?
Can I add, it isn't as risky as you
might think because Yale will take you back if it
fails in a couple of years.
One of our very early employees was a
Yaley who had had an undergraduate experience somewhat
like you're describing where I think he had
actually taken some time off to work on startups.
I think he came back, finished his degree
and is now a partner at Benchmark, one of
the firms I had on that slide.
But while they're thinking, can I ask you...
I emphasize the core values at Yale.
Yes.
I'm a member of the Yale community at
Goldman Sachs and it strikes me that Facebook is
totally different.
Maybe I'm wrong.
Can you tell me what
are the core values at Facebook?
I mean, if I were to read that list
that I just gave you from Goldman Sachs, how would
it sound to the Facebook people?
Yeah.
So I think there's similarities and differences.
I think each of us has a core constituency
who we wake up thinking about them, go to
the gym, probably dream about them and know
that whether or not we serve that constituency
will determine the success or failure of the company.
And at Goldman, that was the clients.
And at Facebook, our number one focus
is the users and the user experience.
And we care a lot about our partners, we
care a lot about our advertisers, we care a lot
about everyone in the ecosystem, but ultimately we
know we have to serve the users as well.
So each company, I think, has almost a maniacal focus.
And so, I think, that's the core.
And I think the other thing that I think
is really important is that we have to have a
maniacal focus on serving one
core constituency, albeit they're different.
Now, in terms of the day-to-day
experience, I do think they're quite different.
I think that what I'm doing
now is quite a bit more creative.
You're not doing spreadsheets.
A little bit, but not...
You're doing stuff.
Yeah, not as much.
And I really love the creative side of the work.
If you think back to from David
Schwartzman's lecture where he mentions that there's no
flexibility in the way that you're working.
There were some cut-ups that were made.
So there were some issues about
też higher já você achört algumas các
frações.
Alex está falando sobre Elijah de
Amagukraft região, parte aqui da colônia.
Allá vamos a selecionar a ilham para a
eleição com o queかm er Quando chegamos à
the number of times that happens,
try to fix them as soon as they do happen,
and just be honest about them
and admit them when we make them.
Could I ask a question of the class?
You set the example.
How many in this class are engineering majors?
Not many.
What, like 5% maybe?
What about science majors?
That looks like 10%.
But you see, you're kind
of in an engineering company, right?
I mean, I don't know exactly what Facebook is,
but you are...
Is there some kind of division here?
I mean, why aren't there more engineers in this class?
That sounds like a question for the class.
Well, I can't ask them because they're not here.
Why are you not in the room?
But, I mean, is there...
It seems like, is there a big cultural difference?
I mean, are engineers...
Are engineers prejudiced against us finance people?
You're there, so...
Look, I think that product design and software engineering
is at the heart of the company,
but as I mentioned, you know,
I was pretty intimidated going in saying,
huh, like I'm going to be a business guy here.
Am I not really going to
be able to have an impact?
And I think the things that
are important for the business people
are, one, to remember what the
core mission of the company is,
which for us is really all about the users.
Two,
to have a sense of what is feasible, right?
So you don't actually have to
know how to write the code
or even necessarily how to mock up the product,
but if you're making recommendations
that we should build things
that are simply technologically not feasible,
you're going to waste people's time
and lose credibility pretty quickly.
And then three, I think when you do the analysis,
engineers are going to want to see
as rigorous analysis as possible,
quantitative analysis when that's relevant,
when that's possible.
And to the extent that you
can bring that to the table,
I think that's helpful.
If you think about the business world at large,
you know, one of the things that's just going
to be increasingly important is
the ability to design, conduct,
and interpret statistically significant valid experiments.
And this sounds like a pretty straightforward thing
that you might learn by maybe
second or third year of college.
And yet you get out into the business world
and you'll find that many of your colleagues,
whether they're coming from MBAs or other backgrounds,
may not actually have that background.
So being able to bring that
sort of rigor to the table,
whether it's at a consumer internet company
or an industrial company, anything else,
I think is very helpful.
Yeah, I'm thinking maybe I should change the name
of this course to financial engineering.
I would bring in the others.
Because it is a, to me, engineering
and finance have a certain connection.
They're both designing devices.
I think we have another question.
Have you thought of going back to graduate school
and how do you see that?
How do you see that playing into a career
like investment banking?
So yeah, I have thought
about going back to graduate school.
I think that all of us want
to be lifelong learners throughout our career, right?
And there's a number of ways you can do that.
Graduate school is one of them.
Another is going into industries where you're just confident
that everyone you're working with is really smart
and they're going to push you hard and not settle
for mediocrity so you just know
you're going to learn by that,
that pressure and that osmosis.
And then I think there's a lot
of simple structured things that you can do as well.
I threw a slide up of a couple
that you can kind of do, you know,
in the comfort of your own living room,
Myers-Briggs and StrengthFinder.
But then also, you know,
you can leverage having, you know,
a workplace to do things
like peer coaching, career coaching,
executive coaching.
So I kind of take a
somewhat agnostic point of view as to,
like, which of these tools I'm
going to use at any given time.
I just know that I constantly want
to be challenging myself and constantly want
to be learning more.
Okay.
I've heard a lot about issues with click-through rates
on various social networking sites.
So if you could talk about,
like, what you think the putative value
of Facebook should be and whether, like,
the current valuation is appropriate.
Yeah, so I'm happy to share a little bit
about click-through rates.
I'll probably defer on the question
of how much the company should be valued at.
So, you know, I think, you know,
I think, you know, I think, you know,
if you, you know, if you're a big company,
you should have at least one click-through rate.
Yeah.
So I'm just going to get
back to the question of, like,
is there a click-through rate?
So, is there, is everyone familiar
with what a click-through rate is?
No. Not everyone.
Okay. So this is just a simple ratio.
It's, let's say you show an ad some number
of times to users on the Internet.
It's the ratio of the number of
times a user clicks on that ad
to the total number of times you showed it.
So if you show an ad
100 times and you get one click,
you have a 1% click-through rate.
And if you think about, well, why are people advertising?
In marketing, there's kind of this concept of this marketing
funnel, which is a little bit silly, but it actually
conveys a useful concept.
Up here is kind of like everyone in the world.
And then here is the people we can actually make
aware of our product.
Then here is the people who
we can actually have an affinity
for our product.
And here is the people who we can actually consider
purchasing our product.
And then people who actually buy it.
And then repeat loyal customers who buy it more and
more, so we get to a narrower and narrower pool.
And what marketers are kind
of constantly trying to do is
push people through this funnel so they can actually
start with someone who may not
know about the product at all
and then actually get them
to buy it again and again.
And so marketers use a variety of different tools.
Online advertising is one, but that represents maybe 15% of
the market, but it's a relatively new one.
And there's plenty of others that go back decades or
centuries, things like television, radio, print.
And these different media play different roles in getting
people through this marketing funnel.
And if you think about where online advertising originally
grew up, it was really towards
the very bottom of this funnel
of, OK, I am looking for a
blue iPod at the best price that I
can either order online or that it's within
five miles of my home.
So I search that on a search engine.
I see a list of vendors.
And in that case, it's really important whether I click
through, because that's basically the determinant of
whether or not we get them
through the next stage in the
marketing funnel.
If you think about Facebook advertising, that is one of
the roles that it can play.
But it can also actually play throughout this entire
marketing funnel, where we have a reach of 500 million
people, and then you can target within that.
And then you can use
things like social context telling you
that your friend might really
love a product to help build
your affinity for it on through this whole funnel.
So for some of it, click-through rate is
relevant.
For other of it, click-through rate really isn't relevant.
And you need to think about other sorts
of measurement, things like companies like Nielsen do,
like polling people and asking
them, OK, you saw this media.
Did it increase your likelihood to buy this product?
Or did it make you aware
of the message that the brand's
trying to convey that you weren't aware of before?
I think it's one of a number
of metrics that kind of go into
assessing the health of the business as a whole.
I think we're essentially out of time.
But let me just say, click-through rates and
marketing sound like profit-oriented.
But it seems to me they have a social purpose.
One thing is that capitalism is being transformed by this
kind of thing, because it gets
people to buy things that they
really need.
It's like your StrengthsFinder or NeedsFinder.
And I have to applaud Facebook and other companies.
Finally, I'm going to invite
you back in another 10 years.
This was great.
Thanks.